James Pickard B.Sc. (Hons)

james.pickard@gmail.com +1 514 802 5105

First-Class Honours degree (University of London). Over 4 years experience in demanding software development roles for a London-based company including assignments for Canadian lottery providers. Strong development and team leadership skills with a focus on best-practice programming. Creative, enthusiastic, problem solver and team player.

Achievements

- Technical lead for a multi-million dollar provincial lottery website.
- 'Rookie of the year 2008' at industry leading London-based software development company.
- Over 80% grade average at university (GPA 4.00+ equivalent^[1])
- Founder of a three-man computer partnership.

[1] http://www.ten-percent.co.uk/conversion-table-for-us-gpa-to-uk-class-degrees

Experience

From June 2013 to January 2014 I was on sabbatical in England while awaiting confirmation of Canadian permanent residence.

February 2008 – June 2013. London, England; Moncton, Canada; Montreal, Canada. Various roles, OpenBet Technologies Ltd.

- Software Engineer for Loto-Québec and British Columbia Lottery Corporation teams. Working with industry leading partners IGT to deliver online gaming systems.
- Technical Lead for the mobile games team. Bringing existing games to the mobile platform. Working with cutting edge technologies including HTML 5, CSS 3, targeting iOS.
- Technical Lead to completion of multi-million-dollar provincial betting website for Atlantic Lottery Corporation. Leading a team of up to 10 people, first point of customer contact, day-to-day managerial and technical roles including line management, code review, requirements analysis, software design specification, system configuration.
- Senior Developer on API team providing an XML interface for bet placement, payments, customer management, liability calculation, event hierarchy.
- Customer-facing experience with industry-leading UK-based bookmakers including Ladbrokes, William Hill, Paddy Power.
- Project design and analysis, requirements gathering and specification writing.
- Ongoing support, including remote administration involving troubleshooting time-critical live issues.

July 2006 - July 2008. Bungay, England.

Self employed web development, network troubleshooting and consulting.

November 2002 – June 2003. Bungay, England.

Partner, Open Computer Solutions.

Founder of computer troubleshooting and sales business.

Skills

General

- Experience architecting scalable, reliable, modular high transaction-volume systems.
- Experience with every stage of the software lifecycle from requirements gathering to deployment, to ongoing maintenance.
- Leadership and management experience with development teams of up to 10 people.
- Database design and development experience with Informix, PostgreSql, MySQL, SQLite. Database administration experience with Informix.
- Proficiency with Linux command line: bash, sed, awk, find, curl, rsync, etc.
- Lots of experience with vim including plugins in vimscript, e.g. https://github.com/euoia/vim-jsbeautify-simple.
- Source control end-user experience with git, subversion, CVS.
- Experience running a small business.
- <u>Tcl</u> Back-end application development: Customer account management, liability calculation, bet placement, social responsibility programs, back-office systems.
 - Integration with third-party APIs: credit card systems, Interac, Bank of Nova Scotia, identity verification, MyThumb SMS, IP location, sports event results systems.
 - Development and maintenance of high transaction-volume XML API for account management.

<u>JavaScript / NodeJS</u> - Game server and lobby system for online games using socket.io <u>https://github.com/euoia/node-games-lobby</u>

- Experience with widely used libraries and patterns: Express, Backbone.js, jQuery, d3, RequireJS.
- Front-end testing using Selenium.
- PHP 3 years experience including PHP 5 and object-oriented features.
 - Bespoke website and content management system built using CakePHP.
 - Bug tracking system and forum for an online game.
 - Content design and editing tool for an online game using Zend framework.
- <u>Scala</u> Implementation of trigram search for Stripe's Capture the Flag competition.
 - Coursera course.
- <u>Go</u> Integration with goraft (an implementation of the raft protocol in go) for a distributed, fault-tolerant database.
- <u>C++</u> University-level exposure, some familiarity with the standard template library.
 - Networked text based role-playing game.
 - Tile based game engine using SDL (OpenGL based) graphics library.
 - 3rd year university project an implementation of Digital Fountain encoder, decoder and benchmark suite.

Python - Web scraping using Beautifulsoup library to display gumtree ads on google maps.

- Raspberry Pi temperature logging application.
- Google AI challenge 2010 entry.
- iOS App which shows average sun exposure during a train journey, 'SunnySide'.
 - Working with Phonegap to bring an HTML5 version of the card game blackjack to Apple's app store.

Qualifications

September 2003 – June 2006 Royal Holloway, University of London B.Sc. Computer Science with Artificial Intelligence, First-class Honours.

Recent interests

Writing nodejs programs. Playing soccer. Online programming challenges such as Stripe capture-the-flag, Google AI challenge, interviewstreet. Learning French. Building things with the Raspberry Pi.

Additional Information

British citizen with Canadian permanent residence. Full clean British & Quebec driving licenses. Fluent English, intermediate level French. Based in Montreal.

References

Excellent references are available upon request.